One thing I really like about momentum is
that
it uses a lot of math. And in this case,
we
will be looking at a 2D momentum question
that
mainly uses math and logic to be able to
solve
it. Momentum is all about deriving
equations,
as you guys probably saw in the previous
two
examples. So in this case, a 2 kilogram
puck
moving east at 4 metres per second, it
would
be first good to draw a compass, so north,
east,
south, west, at 4 metres per second
collides
with a 0.3 kilogram puck moving north at
2.5
metres per second on frictionless ice, so
you
would probably need to use momentum. They
stick
together after the collision. And that's
good,
as we've seen before, because that means
it's
an inelastic equation. And if it's
inelastic,
elastic, that means that there will be one
single
mass after. You can treat it as one single
system
after they collide. Find the magnitude of
the
final velocity and find the direction. So
first,
let's do magnitude. We can map this out,
for
example, a 0.2 kilogram puck moving east.
So let's say east is the x direction and
north
is the y direction. If it's moving east at
4.00
metres per second, and this puck is moving
north,
0.300 kilograms, at 2.5 metres
per second, well, if they stick together,
their
final velocity will be something along the
lines
of this way. So, north of east.
And we want to find the magnitude of that.
So, if we treat north as
the y direction and we treat east as the x
direction,
we can actually split the final vector
into
two components. We can split it into the y
component
and the x component. And this question is
really
good, because you don't have to do
anything
to this vector alone. We know that the y
component
of this momentum is 0.
It's going completely towards the east
axis.
So its y component is 0, but its x
component
is whatever the momentum is.
So, let's call this puck A, let's call
this
puck B. So the momentum of A in the y
component
is mass times velocity in the y direction.
And since velocity in the y direction for
puck
A is 0, that means that the momentum here
is
0. However, in the x direction, the
momentum
would be equal to mass times velocity in
the
x direction. And the velocity in the x
direction
is 4 metres per second. So, it's 0.2 times
4.00
metres per second. It's kind of like
kinematics
in a sense that you will have to be using
trig
or splitting vectors into y and x
components.
And you would get 0.8 kilograms metres per
second.
And now we will do the same thing for the
other
puck. Initially, sorry, P B, because this
is puck B. P B y, well it has a velocity
in
the y direction, 2.5 metres per second.
So m v y, which is 0.300 times 2.5.
And that would be 0.75 kilograms
per metres per second.
On the other hand, the x component of this
puck's
velocity, well it's not going left, it's
not
going right, so the x component is 0.
m v x. So v x is 0, which means there's
not
going to be momentum in the x direction.
So
basically what I've done so far is I've
looked
at the two pucks and I've split them into
x
and y directions. Now we can calculate the
total
momentum, or we can calculate the total
momentum
in the x direction and the y direction.
The total momentum p final, I'll do this
in
green, p final, let's call that, in the x
direction, will just be equal to p a x
plus
p b x,
because there's no thing. So the total
momentum
in the x direction is 0.8 kilograms metres
per
second. Same thing for the final total
momentum
in the y direction, p a y plus p b y,
which
is 0 plus 0.75.
So this would be 0.75 kilograms per metres
per
second. And that would be the momentum in
the
x direction and the y direction. So
knowing
the momentum in the x direction and the y
direction,
we can actually calculate the speed,
because
we know the mass. The mass of the system
after
they stick together would be just a sum,
0.200
plus 0.300.
So m total is 0.200 plus 0.300, which
is 0.500 kilograms.
And now let's calculate the speed in the x
and
y direction, respectively. So we can do
speed
final x is equal to momentum over mass, p
of f x over mass total mass, because p
equals
m v, so we just rearrange that equation.
So you get 0.8 over 0.5, so you just
multiply
it by two, and you get 1.6 metres per
second
in the x direction. Same thing for the y.
The final y velocity would be equal to p f
y
over m total.
And if you don't get what I'm doing, it's
really
important to revisit or replay the video
to
see what I did, because this is really,
really
important. I basically split the vectors
up.
And if you don't know how I did that, you
probably
won't be understanding what I'm doing
right
now. But if you do, this will be pretty
straightforward
for you. 2.5 and it would be 1.5 metres
per
second. And now we have basically
everything
we need. This is now back to beginner
vectors
and scalars. This is the final velocity we
need.
We know that y velocity, v-final y, we
know v
f x. So what we can do is we can bring
v-final x
over here, like I've talked about in
previous
units. You can bring this here, and you
could
use Pythagorean theorem to calculate for
the
final. So the final velocity is the square
root
of 1.6 squared plus 1.5 squared.
And when you type that into the
calculator,
it is 1.5 squared, 2.19, or
sig figs, 2.2. 2.2 metres per second.
And that will be the final answer for A.
Now
for number 2, it's also pretty
straightforward.
After we've solved the final velocity in
both
the x direction and the y direction, we
can
basically calculate the angle as well.
Since
the question asks north of east, we want
to
measure the angle relative to north. So we
want
to measure, this would be north, so we
to measure this angle. Now, when we
measure
this angle, we will have to use tangent,
because
we have v-final of y and v-final of x.
So let me just copy and paste this diagram
over
down here, and I can edit it a bit.
Okay, so v-final of x, what we calculated,
is 1.6
metres per second, and this is 1.5 metres
per
second. And we want to find theta. Well,
we
know that tan of theta is equal to
opposite
over adjacent, so tan of theta equals 1.6
over
1.5. And now we can just solve for theta.
And when we solve for theta, we have tan
of
negative 1, 1.6 over 1.5.
And it would be 46.8 degrees.
So, relative to the north axis, theta
would
be 46.8 degrees. So, if the vector
would look like this, this would be 46.8
degrees,
and that would be our final answer.
Our direction would be north 46.8 degrees
east.
And that's basically how you get the angle
and
the velocity. So the final velocity vector
ultimately,
this would be the answer to part b by the
way,
but the final velocity vector would be 2.2
metres
per second north 46.8 degrees east.
And that would be your final direction and
velocity
of the puck system.
And that's how you solve 2D system
equations.
You basically have to split the momentum
into
x and y components, and then after you
split
them, you can add them if they're
inelastic,
or do your energy equation if they're
inelastic.
And with those different components of
your
momentums, you can calculate their x and y
velocities.
And after that, it's just a matter of
applying
what we've learned in the past to get the
overall
velocity and the overall direction using
tan.
Thank you for listening, and I hope you
learned
something. Bye!